[Music]
and we are live
uh good evening and good day everybody
welcome to the 31st
live episode of ask abhijit today we
talk about education i take your
questions and answer them
and before we get into it let me take a
look at who all is there
so i can see dharmendra das hello good
evening
jyoti patel good evening
yousef bobby tatagat
vaishali
good evening good day everybody it's
great to see you all
so let's get into the questions
i have a lot of questions that i'm going
to answer tonight so let's start with
question number one
and question number one is by keshav
how do you suggest we make the sanskrit
language of our national language when
people of different states
will object to it and over 99 percent of
indians don't understand the sanskrit
language
so this is a very common question that
most indians don't understand sanskrit
it's going to be a lot of hard work to
learn this new language
well you know what the truth is that
sanskrit is our matra bhasha
when i say the term matru basha what
language is it
matra basha we all understand this term
matra basha it's a sanskrit term
right when i say the the the term
rashtra hit everybody understands that
that is sanskrit when you say bharat
mata that is sanskrit when you say
akanda bharat
that is sanskrit your name keshav is a
sanskrit name my name abhijit
is a sanskrit name we use sanskrit every
single day we use sanskrit vocabulary we
use
terminology sanskrit is embedded in our
lives
and we simply don't realize it sanskrit
is our mother tongue it is our
civilizational language
it is the mother tongue of our mother
tongues whether you speak
any language in india you will have
plenty of sanskrit vocabulary
in it so sanskrit is the foundation of
india's culture
and civilization whenever india was
unified as one
entire political entity it has always
been at the forefront
of india's culture and civilization and
even when india was fragmented
even today we don't realize it but
sanskrit is at the
at the core of our existence and
communication
but we simply don't understand it we
simply don't realize it 99
of people in india don't understand
sanskrit this is what we believe
and it's not in it is not the case so
we need to look beyond our what what
beyond our conditioning the conditioning
that our education system has given us
many of us i know that we take the
sanskrit language as one of the
one of the subjects in our education and
the way it is taught
is so painful that it feels like it's
some alien language the way they
it's just the way it is thought it's not
really that difficult a language to
learn it's the one of the easiest
and most logical languages to learn and
yet we
grow up and we live with these
misunderstandings
so so the fact is that sanskrit is
our mother tongue whether we realize it
or not we simply have to get back in
touch with it
so that's the answer to your second
question i'll get back to your first
question
soon
okay uh we know that many travelers came
to ancient
india from china from middle east europe
etc then
how did they communicate with us since
our language
is completely different from them
so let me demonstrate to you how
these foreign people foreigners
communicated with us i'm going to show
you a very short clip
take a look
foreign
so that's a clip from a chinese movie
it's about the life of the
great chinese monk shuan zhang who came
to india to
gain knowledge most people who came to
india from other countries
came either to gain knowledge or they
came to trade with india
to engage in commercial activities and
they all spoke the lingua franca of
india which was sanskrit
they all learned sanskrit sanskrit was
the highest civilizational language in
the entire known universe
where india was a free nation it was a
free culture was before the past 1000
years of
of the invasions sanskrit was the
highest language of culture throughout
asia sanskrit was spoken and various
sanskrit derived languages were spoken
throughout central asia
in in the northern part beyond the
himalayas north of the himalayas which
is now part of china it was never
earlier part of china
etc and the chinese communicated with
our people
in our language sanskrit and our people
went there
our scholars went there and translated
this sanskrit text into chinese and
that's how
buddhism entered china and it's become
an integral part of china it's there
even today
china has the largest buddhist
population in the world
and this buddhism so to say it
incorporates the worship of many indian
gods so that's the point
china the chinese and and the skittions
and the greeks they all learned sanskrit
and that's how they communicated with us
so that is the value of sanskrit my
friends i keep saying that
sanskrit needs to be our civilizational
language there's a reason for it
it was the greatest language in the
world it was
adopted widely and we need to bring the
status back
for example in china the ancient word
for
india in china was tianjin which means
the center of heaven that was india's
status in the past
and today unfortunately for no fault of
our own
our education system imbues us with this
slave mentality
this inferiority complex that yeah yeah
we are we are inferior and
in the west is better or the chinese are
better etc
we are historically the greatest
civilization
in the history of the of the in the
known history of the world
so we need to regain that status and we
need to take steps to do that
so that's the entire and that is where
you talk about education reforms but
because that is the core of the matter
so i hope that answers this question
richard asks what about the south
indians who love english so much that
they will riot
if you try to replace it with sanskrit
and prince agarwal
asks your ideas are great but how can we
replace english with sanskrit without
conflict in the modern in
in the indian state so you guys
are right there's a great deal of
resistance to change
uh right now as of today in southern
india especially in places like tamil
nadu and kerala
there is this great resistance and
hatred
towards sanskrit and towards hinduism
because it is it is not the fault of the
people of the
the of these states that they have this
attitude
towards sanskrit and towards indian
culture and hinduism as a whole
and they have this chauvinistic
supremacist mindset that tamil
is superior to sanskrit etcetera and
there is this language war
which came for sanskrit game or tamil
game first etc
all of this is the consequence of
decades of
chauvinistic and and separatist politics
see politics is all about creating
divisions
politics is all about creating divisions
and exploiting those divisions
creating the sense of persecution
creating a siege mentality
and exploiting that by saying that we
are going to save you we are the only
saviors we are going to restore your
pride we are going to restore
your dignity you have been enslaved for
thousands of years by brahminical
patriarchy and sanskritization
and this is a white skin north indians
in this aryans and we dravidians
are actually older and all that so this
is all political
narratives india has always been one
but because of the past six seven
decades of this
chauvinistic separatist politics that's
why
and which has seeped through into
education media everywhere
that's why the people of a couple of
southern states they have this attitude
and they they have this belief through
no fault of their own i have been to
tamil nadu the people are wonderful
lovely people
very nice people the friendliest people
but they all have this attitude because
they genuinely believe
that they have been persecuted and their
and their culture is different and
separate
and all that so what needs to happen you
are right there is going to be
resistance
there is going to be resistance if we
try to re
revise and reform the system and make
sense with the national language there's
going to be resistance
so what's the solution the solution is
the right
leadership see if you look at that's
that's the reason why we have to study
history because if we study history we
can find solutions whenever india has
been unified
as one entire single
civilizational and political entity it's
always been
because there was a great superhero
of a leader who was able to unify
this country this country is very
complex it's very diverse there's a
great deal of plurality
there's a great deal of apparent
dissimilarity in culture and language
and so many things
and yet it has one culture and
civilization overall but to unify it
properly you need
a leader of of a great stature
and that sort of leader doesn't come
across we don't
we don't find such leaders very often
it's usually somebody who comes along
once in a century
or maybe even once in a millennium right
or once in 500 years
so we are for the past 1000 years
waiting for a leader of that sort of
stature you know
they like the old chakravarthy samaras
like chandragupta maurya or or
or the great samudra gupta
or raja raja chola or even somebody like
shivaji maharaj
so we need somebody of that stature
today's politicians are pygmies
compared to that right so
it will take somebody of almost
superhuman
fortitude and stature and willpower
to unify the country and when a leader
like that comes
when such a leader emerges in this
country despite the mediocre political
system
and all the resistance then only will
that person be able to unify the country
and unify the country civilizationally
culturally linguistically etc
so so declaring sanskrit the national
language
is doesn't mean that we cannot destroy
the other languages i am talking about a
two language formula every child should
learn
two languages the civilizational
language sanskrit and the mother tongue
both should be given equal importance
there is no question of any supremacy
but
this can only be done when you have a
leader of enormous
willpower and fortitude and only then
will this happen so that's what we need
in this country we need genuine
leadership we don't need politicians
politicians think short term they think
five years at the time
and they think about being popular
popularity popularity is
essential to success in politics in
leadership
see the difference between politicians
and leaders is this politicians
will not succeed unless they are popular
so they have to take populist measures
leaders will fail at leadership unless
they take
deeply unpopular decisions for the
long-term good
so that's why our system is designed to
churn out mediocre leaders fake leaders
politicians so that's what india needs
india needs
change change significant deep
revolutionary reformative change i'm not
talking about
about a revolution in the marxist sense
no i abhor that
india needs reforms but revolutionary
reforms
proper non-violent reforms that
strengthen the country
not divide it or fragment it that's
what's needed
manoj asked manoj says my wife did a
diploma in
information technology from a government
polytechnic college
company companies hire only degree
holders and not diploma holders
why have they started this diploma
education you
bring up an excellent point manage this
is infuriating
why do they give why do they why do they
offer degrees or diplomas
that have no value they are fooling
people
the education system has become a
commercial education system it's all
about making money
fool the people okay you don't want a
two-year degree three-year degree get a
one year diploma
but at the end of the day after you get
that piece of paper in your hand and you
go out of the job market
you find it has no value they are
fooling people they should
there should be a law that that debarts
universities colleges educational
institutions from offering
degrees or diplomas or any certificate
which doesn't have any
real real life real world value so this
is a scam i said like i said in the
previous episode episode 30
that the indian education system is a
scam it is a scam that leeches of the
people of india
it gives you degrees in exchange for
cash and time you have to spend two
years three years
slaving away and performing certain
rituals and if you perform those rituals
correctly and if you pay the right
amount of money then they will give you
a piece of paper
that will basically be your passport to
hopefully getting some kind of a job
it's a goddamn scam and it needs to stop
these people need to stop fooling the
nation
om asks what reforms need to take place
so that we can create more jobs
look what is a job it's it's uh some
kind of service that you
uh provide in exchange for money now
does this country need services this
country is a poor third world country
even today
the the per capita gdp is less than that
of bangladesh
right so we definitely need a lot of
change in the country
we need a lot of infrastructure building
our infrastructure is abysmal
we need a great deal of work in the
country
reconstruction of the country we don't
realize it because we are used to living
in this thing we think
this is this is the best place in the
world to live in it's not it's terrible
the living standards are abysmal we need
an
enormous amount of new infrastructure so
all that will require
jobs right but that is not being done
why is it not being done
because the politicians are happy with
the thing with the way things are
so how do we create jobs first of all
start creating infrastructure in the
country
new roads new highways new railway lines
new airports new
all of that secondly uh we need
many industries in this country so start
those in the industries instead of
importing things from abroad for example
just one example out of
out of a million is the defense industry
we can start manufacturing all our
equipment right here in india
so that will create the tens of
thousands of jobs start ship building
our
our navy is in in a terrible condition
we need at least 300 new ships
to keep up with the rise of china and if
we were to if we had to build 300 new
ships in the next 10 15 20 years
we'll need a lot of new shipyards a lot
of people working in these places a lot
of people designing these things
that is jobs we need more planes we need
more submarines
we need more tanks we need so much
defense equipment artillery
and whatnot that requires jobs so if we
do
and what about tourism tourism is it it
creates an entire ecosystem of its own
if india starts to unlock its and
unleash its tourism potential it's going
to add at least a trillion dollars to
its economy to its gdp
and that is going to create an enormous
tourism ecosystem job ecosystem you know
lots of new jobs will
be created because of that so there is
so much we can do with this country
there is so much potential
but the politicians are happy to to keep
on doing this rent seeking
what is rent seeking you don't create
anything new of value but whatever value
exists in the country
you try to extract money in exchange for
giving the value
so it's like you you're taking the the
population hostage
so that's what today's politics and
leadership so-called leadership
is all about politicians need to start
unleashing reforms in this country that
create jobs jobs can be created
it's not hard i mean right now the
entire
agricultural sector is basically what is
it it's a vote bank
so keep the kisan happy keep giving free
things to the kisan and they'll keep
voting for you
that is the formula right now 58 of
india is occupied in agriculture but
agriculture accounts for only 16 or 17
or 18
of our gdp that is shocking we can
we can modernize agriculture you know
and make it way more efficient and free
up all this excessive manpower
and put them in actual nation building
but that's not being done
so i'll tell you what needs to be done
if i were to if i were to say what needs
to be done in one word
end corruption so what's the definition
of corruption
we think that corruption means giving
bribes or taking bribes that's not the
case
when a system does not
serve the people it is supposed to serve
when this when a system does not
carry out its stated function but does
something else entirely
that is corruption and india's entire
governance system is corrupt
so we need to end corruption where is
the war against corruption where is it
we all face corruption in our day-to-day
lives
whether we speak about it or not don't
we anytime you interface with
any government well any any organ of the
government you're going to face
corruption
corruption it's is what's setting india
back
it is this that that is not allowing
india to unleash its productivity
and creativity and and unleash its
economy properly
right entrepreneurship is almost
impossible in this country because you
have corruption if you start becoming
successful you're gonna have to just not
just pay taxes
you're gonna have to pay some additional
taxes which are
which take a number of various names but
it's all corruption
and that's why people get the hell out
of this country so this needs to end
and then only will be able to create
more jobs and to
totally free this country and
allow the people and the country to
realize their full potential
so we need to end corruption where is
the battle against corruption
where is the war against corruption i
don't see any sign of it unfortunately
very sad to say
mandar says mundar asks should we
reorient
our education expenditure towards lower
education
rather than higher education it's an
interesting
question mandar i would say that
a lower education is extremely important
because it's the formative stage of any
human being's life
so what you the ideas that you imbibe
during the first five
10 15 years of your life they they stay
with you forever
if you if you acquire certain beliefs at
that stage they're going to stay with
you forever almost it's
very hard to to de-program your mind of
certain things
so yes the uh lower education is
extremely important we need to
definitely take it very seriously but
higher education is what
prepares with which creates the final
product right so if you have to acquire
skills that have real world value it's
all about higher education so i what i
would say is that both
are equally important but if we were to
start reforms
genuine reforms in education in our
country it has to start at the lower
level
at the lower education level because
that's how see if you
try and impose certain reforms at the
higher education level
but those students are already
conditioned in certain ways then they
are going to
reject those new ideas and thoughts and
they're not going to do well
so it this reform process has to start
at the very lowest level
and you should give we need to give it
about 10 or 20 years for it to go
through
and and percolate through the entire
education system so it's not
a one week or one month or one year
process it's
it's it takes a generation to achieve
genuine
genuine lasting change so i would say
that we need to reorient
our reformative uh if we were if the
government would someday
wake up and and try and do genuine
reforms
it should start at the lowest level and
then it should go progressively upwards
in a logical iterative
manner but i would say that we need to
allocate
expenditure equally to the lower
education system as well as the higher
education system because
both are equally important for the
country it's all about the national
interest
so if the individual does well the
nation also does well
and that's how it works so it's about
the individual's interest
and and by extension
the national interest
akash asks what is the prime reason
behind the fact that even after more
than 70 years
since we got independence we are being
taught the same rigid macaulay and
system of education
nothing has been done by the government
to rectify it is it because the
governments don't care or because the
system is considered as the new standard
education in the world or of education
in the world or because the left lobby
is supporting it with all their might
see i'll tell you what i
i am very critical of our politicians of
our leadership of our government in the
field of education and many other things
because
unless you criticize them they know
unless there is a significant amount of
criticism they will not change
first of all secondly the thing is this
see
our politicians our le our leaders etc
the people who are in charge of various
uh
organs of government various leadership
positions they have all come through the
education system
and if they feel i would say that the
education system has brought given them
success
and therefore it's a good system right
they are all
invested in this system some of them
even benefit and profit from it i'm not
seeing everybody i'm not saying
everybody
some of them definitely do right so
there's a great deal of collusion
it's a close-knit self-serving ecosystem
you have politicians you have the uh
the corporate uh education system you
have the commercial education system
you're the tuition classes the coaching
classes
they are all feeding off each other in
some sense etc
so they are very much invested in the
system and even some politicians
who will definitely be honest and they
have they would have a great deal of
integrity they will also feel that this
system
is what gave them success and therefore
they wanted to continue
i'll tell you after a certain age every
human being becomes close-minded
they stop being open to new ideas i
think it's around the age of 40 that
people become close-minded
and they simply are not
willing to entertain new ideas or
something
that clashes with their worldview
and that's why we need younger leaders
so that is the reason in my opinion why
there is so much
there is there's so much there is so
much inertia in this country they are
doing nothing to change the system even
though
there is now a little bit of a little
bit of em
i mean some talk about changing or or
rectifying some of the more egregious
portions of our history syllabus because
some of them are
just totally blatantly false so there
may be some reforms in that but that is
not all
the entire system is it needs to be
reformed
so unless and until we find a leader of
genuine vision
who can push through the reforms the
country needs it's going to continue
like
that's the way i see it unfortunately as
of today at least as of now
siddharth asks when you say that
education the education system of our
country is very poor
do you include the colleges universities
institutions or do you just mean to say
the schooling system that is from the
first to the 12th grade
i mean to say my my friend that the
entire education of
con system of our country is poor it's
it's
it's defective it's rotten from the very
top to the very bottom from the very
bottom to the very top
everything is terrible in a terrible
shape it simply doesn't serve the
country it doesn't serve the system
it doesn't serve the students the
stakeholders
of any education system are the students
and the country
the education system of india it doesn't
serve the students
it doesn't serve the country it serves
the politicians and the business people
it's a commercial system it's all about
making money
issuing degrees in exchange for money so
this is something i went into a great
deal of detail in yesterday's episode
episode 30
so i would say take a look at that take
a listen
and i have gone into detail in that so
basically
the answer to your question is the
entire system from top to bottom
is decrepit it's corrupt it's rotten it
needs to
be overhold completely
shuribal asks how important is the
revival of the ancient vishwa with the
vidyalayas
universities of this country like vikram
shira
taksha sheila will they be of any
relevance in this modern world you know
what somebody i think
there was some effort to revive nalanda
i think they have
started a new nalanda university or
something the problem is that they are
using the macaulay and education system
in these new
revamped universities the same old
masters degree phd
bachelor's degree that that nonsense
they are implementing the colonial
corrupt education system
in this new universities that they have
named after the old ones so what's the
point of reviving these ancient
universes and
enforcing a corrupt colonial commercial
syllabus
or system in there there is no point
reviving anything
unless we first fix the education system
the education system should serve the
people and the country
when we can do that then universities
then every university will suddenly
start flourishing
and start producing superstars and
producing what india needs
so the solution is not to revive the
universities that were destroyed by the
by the barbarians yes i would definitely
like
to see those universities revived but we
need to first fix the education system
and only then should we try and
revive the old universes that were
destroyed it would be a great
uh it would be a great insult
to those universities if one were to
implement
the corrupt colonial commercial system
of education in them
so we need to fix the education system
first
ashutosh asks government jobs versus
private jobs versus business
what do people prefer in other countries
like china japan us etc
and what's the best direction for indian
students youths all right yeah
in other countries people like to go
into any job
that is best suited for them based upon
their aptitude
skills interests and all that so if it
is a government job they'll go for a
government job if it's a private job
it's a business
entrepreneurship whatever it is or
freelancing
or gig economy whatever whatever
is best for you that's what you want to
go into in other countries there are
lots of options
in india until very recently the only
option was to be a government bureaucrat
the only stability you would have in
life was if you were able to
miraculously get a government job
somehow so there are
even today very few avenues that that
people can take
you can either take a government job or
you can go into some it firm
or you can start a small business
somewhere there are very few
options available let's say somebody is
has a great musical talent
great guitarist what job options does a
guitarist have
so they are forced to give up their
primary skill and try and become a
businessman or a chartered accountant
or a school teacher or something right
so what the government of india needs to
do
is to open up the economy properly end
corruption let people start their own
businesses stop harassing
entrepreneurs stop harassing businessmen
right business people
let the economy flourish in all
directions
then people will have lots of options to
choose from
right so that's what happened needs to
happen what is the best direction for
indian students in youth
do what is best for you the system
doesn't love you
the system hates merit this system
identifies and destroys silent and it
promotes
mediocrity i would appeal to the
students of india the students who are
listening to me right now
please do what is best for you do what
maximizes your potential
if you have to go abroad and get a good
education there go abroad and get a good
education
be the best person you can be achieve
your full potential
and maybe someday if you're abroad and
india becomes a better country again
then maybe that at that time you can
come back to india and contribute what
you can
but first of all develop yourself
invest yours in invest in yourself if
you can get the good education in your
opinion from
in india do it here otherwise go abroad
go wherever is best for you
get your the best education you can
acquire
and become the best version of yourself
achieve your full potential and only if
you do that
can you someday someday come back and
serve your country so that's what i
would say that is the best option for
you
saurabh asks uh in our country
teacher to student ratio is very poor
can it be considered to be a problem for
indian education and how
and if so how to overcome it the teacher
to student ratio in india
is abysmal uh even in good schools you
know good private schools where you
spend lacks of rupees per year typically
the student the teacher to student ratio
will be 1 to 30 40
and in regular private schools it will
be like one teacher for 60 70 80
students
it's terrible right you can't teach
a mob i mean it's impossible for a
teacher to
put anything across to such a large
number of students so there's no
individual attention at all
there is no connection you can just sit
in the back of the class and do whatever
you want
as long as you just pretend like you're
listening everything is fine
so that is one of the major deficiencies
in india's
education system we need more teachers
but first of all we need to fix the
system
make it rational make it serve the
people in the national interest
and then we need more teachers more good
quality teachers today's teachers are
also
mediocre so these are the problems we're
facing one of the major problems like
you pointed out is the
terrible abysmal teacher to student
ratio so even if you're teaching
this this terrible education this falls
history etc
even then you're not able to do it
efficiently because there are so many
students who take care of
so yes it's one of the major problems in
india
hemanth asks what can we do about our
existing bad
assets teachers poor colleges
schools etc which are just printing
degrees and don't care about the
students future
what can we do we can reform the
education system i gave those
suggestions yesterday a proper planned
thing
a set of suggestions i gave yesterday
about the lower education system the
higher education system
that can serve as a set of guidelines
for anyone who actually is
serious about changing things so we need
to first
fix the education system in that manner
and what do we do about the existing bad
assets there are
many bad teachers as we all know well
what we can do is this so i hate this
term because it has very bad
connotations
it's called re-education i'm not using
it in the chinese
perspective in the chinese context or
the russian context in china and russia
re-education means basically you know
something very bad what i mean is
we need to give these non-performing
assets these bad teachers poor teachers
a chance to go through a training
process again
and and acquire the skills that will
actually enable them to
give a proper education to the students
so we need to give everybody one chance
to reform themselves so that's that's
what i would term as a re-education in
the real sense
give them a six-month course of of how
to teach properly
and actually care about the students etc
and then give them a chance and see how
they do if they still don't do well then
well they can go somewhere else and find
some other kind of
employment or or occupation and
once we reform the education system
these poor schools and poor colleges
will become better
because the system will be better so
that's what we need to do first of all
change the education system reform it
thoroughly overhaul it thoroughly
and secondly re-educate the teachers
give them one chance and
induct lots of new young teachers who
are
who are energetic who are motivated and
who actually care about the students and
all that right so that's what we need to
do
advaith asks should the ranking system
be demolished
because most students get judged by the
rank
and end up getting demotivated in
studying i
totally agree with you this ranking
system is a consequence
of the rat race that india has become
india is a land of great artificial
scarcity everything is scarce
there are very few good colleges very
few good schools very few good
universities there are very few seats
in all these institutions and therefore
you need to get the highest possible
marks the highest possible rank
it is a terrible system it is
extraordinarily stressful for students
it robs children of their childhood so
this ranking system should be abolished
or demolished like you say
what needs to happen is we need to have
a standardization of education
throughout the country
and everybody should be given either a
a this grading system you know a letter
based reading abcd etc
or just say whether they've crossed the
minimum threshold of passing or not
or either you can give them some kind of
percentile ranking so whether you
scored in the 90th percentile or 80th
percentile or 97th percentile whatever
so something like that needs to be
incorporated in the education system
this ranking system is
useless it doesn't indicate any kind of
success in later life
these students who perform the best in
india's education system
typically perform very poorly in life
and students who are mediocre in
the education system who never got high
ranks they typically do very well
in actual life so this system of ranking
and all
it is just it needs to it needs to go
it is pointless
akash asks what kind of jobs will be
there in the near future
will freelancing dominate the market so
i would say that certain jobs will never
go away certain jobs are
evergreen they will always stay uh
banking
so we will always have banks as far as i
can see unless you have cryptocurrency
coming in everywhere
and that becomes a de facto standard but
certain jobs like
construction for example bricklaying
road laying
gardening carpentry etc
i think some jobs will always be there
doctors will always be there
as far as i can see at least the next 20
30 years i think
but yes in in the near future the entire
job market
is going to change it's all going to be
technology driven so it will be best for
everybody to get some sort of
technical technological expertise get
tech savvy
understand the internet understand
computers and acquire some skills
because yes
in the future it's not going to be
degree driven it's going to be skills
driven what skills do you have can you
make a website do you know how to code
html css java
javascript python various programming
skills various
uh graphic design skills which is
actually art it's art
but you do it on these software packages
like photoshop or
adobe premiere pro or whatever it is
right video editing graphic designing
digital arts digital painting so all of
these skills
are going to be very valuable uh people
may be able to
earn full-time livelihoods just by
freelancing and by the gig economy
it may very very well end up dominating
the market it's very possible
so people will no longer have to go and
get a job a stable job
they'll be able to work from home
especially if they if they have
high quality skills so it is definitely
a very significant possibility
and people will be able to join the
created economy we create various kinds
of
products whether it's digital digital
products or physical products
and today because of the reach of the
internet you'll be able to sell all of
this online
in various platforms so the future is
going to be very different or the entire
education system may very
well end up becoming obsolete in a
decade or so
everything is online now even learning
is online and people are asking
themselves already
why the hell am i paying so much money
to learn online when i can get the same
or even a better education for free
online
so things are changing very drastically
right now we are in the
in the midst of a revolutionary process
of change this decade is going to
transform the entire world
so i think you are right akash that we
will definitely see a great
increase in freelancing jobs people may
be able to
earn excellent livelihoods freelancing
so it it is definitely a possibility a
strong possibility
in the coming years
on mole asks amid the notorious
malfunctioning of the government
agencies why does isro stand out as a
rare
stellar organization with numerous
accomplishments
what should the government learn from
these accomplishments to infuse more
competence in other agencies
or public sector units very good
question on mole
so yes compared to other government
agencies
isro has performed very well it is a
very high achieving
organization it has
accomplishments that have surpassed the
accomplishments of other countries of
many other countries etc
and i think the reason for this is that
the government
has not
imposed an enormous amount of
bureaucracy or israel
the scientists are allowed
to uh take up projects that the
government gives them
and they're allowed to basically carry
out these projects without
too much bureaucratic interference take
the lca pages
project the fighter jet project which
india has now
completed i would say it's still
evolving we are creating a
better version of the fighter jet etc
but it took about 30
more than three decades to develop this
fighter jet and the reason for that is
that the
the various governments kept on
interfering they would keep on changing
the requirements
of the fighter jet so if the fighter
plane was supposed to be let's say 15
meters long
some government agent would come and say
no some some government official would
come and say no now it has to be 15.5
meters long
so the entire thing is to be redesigned
then they will say no we need the wings
to be this size or something
other because they were getting
inducements from foreign companies
and foreign countries to buy foreign
weaponry
and that's why they kept on sabotaging
the lca pages project
and when a new government came in came
in
and they decided to take the com
the project to completion to its natural
logical conclusion
it happened so our scientists our
engineers are
very much capable of producing
world-class products
it's just that the government and the
bureaucracy keeps interfering
and isro i think has not fallen victim
to this too much at least
so that's why it's able to do well and
yet i am disappointed with
the with what isro is not being allowed
to do isro
is a bunch of really talented people
brilliant scientists
as we know they can do things and do
brilliant things
so why is israel not being allowed to
develop reusable rockets
rockets that land on the road it will
save so much money right
why don't we do it why isn't israel
allowed being allowed to develop more
powerful rockets
that can reach the moon in three days
instead of thirteen instead of three
three months why why are we stuck at the
pslv in gslv level why can't we have a
rocket that's 10 times more powerful
why can't we actually compete with the
heavyweights like like the americans and
the russians
or the chinese why is isro not being
allowed to develop better technology it
has the capability
if we can produce a psle in pslv and
gslv
kind of rocket it's actually trivial
to multiply that by 10 and create a
rocket that's 10 times more powerful
you just have to attach more boosters
and those boosters should
ideally be reusable boosters so isro has
the capability to do this but it's not
being allowed to do it
so there is a lack of political will
and yet isro is actually a successful
organization compared to let's say drdo
so why does other why do other
organizations
and agencies like drdo fail why
are they so mediocre even they have the
same scientists the same caliber of
scientists
so what's going wrong so let me tell you
a story about drdo
so drdo was founded in the year 1958
and coincidentally another agency
was also founded in 1958 that was darpa
d-a-r-p-a let me show you the wikipedia
page for darpa hang on
just give me a second let me share that
that wikipedia page
one second
all right here we are this is called
darpa
defense advanced research projects
agency darpa it's an american agency it
was founded as you can see
in 1958 right 63 years ago
and it's it has 220 employees
darpa and its budget is about three and
a half billion dollars
as of 2019. so this is one of the
most brilliant agencies in the world
they have developed such incredible
technology like the stealth
aircraft and and so much more and
there's so much technology they have
developed which is
still classified it has not been
announced in the world they are the ones
i believe who invented the internet
gps weather satellites stealth
technology voice interfaces
the personal computer the internet etc
etc etc
they have developed technology that's
out of the world
always they have been the leaders in
technology development
so that's darpa 1958. now let's take a
look at drdo also 1958.
so remember darpa has 220 employees with
a budget of three and a half billion
dollars roughly
let's take a look at drdo also 1958
their budget is about 1.6 billion which
is about half
of darpa and they have 30
000 employees out of which only 5000 are
scientists
do you see the problem my friends
do you see the problem drdo has
a similar kind of budget but they have
000 employees out of which only 5000 are
scientists which means 25 000 are either
bureaucrats or administrators or
sweepers or peons or clerks or god knows
what
so this scientific organization has been
turned into an employment generation
scheme
for people who are not scientists and
that and still this budget which is
going into it is called a scientific
budget
even though the majority of it is spent
on the salaries of these worthless
non-performing non-scientific employees
i'm not saying they are worthless
individuals
but they don't serve the organization
and its purpose its stated purpose
the stated purpose of drdo is to produce
scientific innovation
for india but its actual purpose is
employment generation
so that's called corruption its actual
purpose
has been subverted so this is the story
of india this is the story of india's
government
they take everything and turn it into
employment generation schemes
in the hope of getting more votes etc in
the
this this thought process is that of
mediocrity
and that is what is the problem with our
leadership and that's why
india doesn't do well in science so i
think isro does better it it has
a better structure and it has less
government interference and that's why
it is doing well
so that is something that should be
replicated in places like darpa and
other places as well and then
things will improve
ankit asks we have a huge population of
people who are not
and who are not graduated
and age of about 30s and 40s etc if
there's a chance
to get them also to be educated or leave
them as they are
why is it a shameful even if we hate to
discuss about it etc
yeah many people don't have a degree
and yet there are so many people with
degrees millions of people with degrees
what knowledge do they have see a degree
doesn't give you
an any any actual knowledge about the
world it just
how do you get a degree you get a degree
by memorizing things and writing essays
in exams
the only skill you learn to acquire a
degree
is how to pass exams that's the only
skill you learn you don't actually learn
any real skills
when you acquire a degree there are many
people who don't have degrees
who have better understanding of the
world and of various
uh domains of knowledge i don't have a
history degree
and let me see talk to any historian so
that's
my point is that you don't need a degree
to
actually have knowledge education
doesn't mean degree education is
actually understanding things
acquiring genuine knowledge acquiring
wisdom that's education
so i i don't care if people don't have
degrees in their 30s and 40s it doesn't
matter
those people may actually have knowledge
that degree holders won't have
my point is that in today's system in
india
unless you have have a paper degree you
don't get jobs you don't get
opportunities
and the people who are given degrees are
not given any actual skills or any
actual knowledge
that is the problem with india system
there are people
who don't have degrees who have a great
deal of knowledge and you have
millions of degree holders who don't
have any real knowledge and through
no fault of their own it's the system
which has done this to them
so that's why we need education reforms
in this country
mimi asks is it really important for
kids to learn algebra trigonometry and
theorems
why don't the teachers ever tell kids
where or how to use them in daily life
why do some science teachers in school
also teach math and english etc in
schools
the whole education system is only a
business how are they getting
recognition from the education board why
does the government give recognition
recognition to every other businessman
to open schools colleges these days
how is it even legal there is no rule of
law in the country by the way
go outside on the street we are supposed
to have traffic rules in the country
is there any traffic rule being obeyed
is there
and done don't blame the people for this
is any traffic rule being enforced
if there is no enforcement people will
do whatever they can
to get ahead so that is the problem
in this country there is no rule of law
the law is there only in the
in the in the papers it's it's all on
paper
it doesn't really exist out there in the
real world
so yeah education is a business it has
become a business the education boards
are all involved in this
politicians are involved in this
governments are involved in this any
businessman business woman can open a
school if they have enough money
it's a money generation scheme it's a
money making machine and it's an
employment generation scheme
the government has left it all to the
business people okay we can't deal with
education you guys start these deemed
colleges and deemed universities
and god knows what and you give out this
paper degrees and that's how we will run
the country
it's shameful really so that's the
situation and that's why i keep
emphasizing that we need to have reforms
and i've given a way forward you know
to as to how to do these reforms a
roadmap
now is it really important for kids to
learn algebra and trigonometry and
calculus and theorems
no and it comes from i'm
i'm saying this i am somebody who has
acquired a ridiculous amount of
knowledge in mathematics because i'm a
physicist right so
i am saying this that you don't need to
learn algebra and trigonometry
and theorems and calculus to be
successful in real life
all you need to learn is basic
arithmetic addition subtraction division
multiplication
fractions and that's about it you don't
need algebra
all you need is arithmetic and that you
can acquire that knowledge you can
acquire by the by the fifth standard
that's all you need so it the education
system is a waste of children's lives
it it imposes years of worthless and
pointless education on them
we don't need any of these topics and
subjects algebra trigonometry we need to
do away with them
unless a student actually once wants to
go into
into science or into higher research in
that case they can learn these things
of their own volition it should not be
forced upon them
so so you're right i agree with you
completely
pink line cabs asks do you think the
education system is the reason why
despite
more advanced technology we are not
making groundbreaking
discoveries or inventions like we did in
ancient india or in the time of einstein
bohar or plank
absolutely it's the education system
that's holding this country back
yesterday i showed how the chinese they
instituted
a step-by-step uh program of reforms
which completely transformed the
education system from 1978 onwards
it was a long process but it was very
meticulously and patiently done
so and they recognized the fact that
technology and science
is at the core of the development and
progress of a country
so today we have advanced technology
that we can use we have this technology
i'm able to talk to you live
because of technology but i am doing it
on a platform that's owned by
an american company we are using
platforms that are owned by by other
nations
our government has not given us any
platform that
unites the country our government is not
investing
in any groundbreaking technology we are
not investing in artificial intelligence
we are not
investing in super computing we are not
investing in machine learning quantum
computing
any of these things we are not allowing
indian companies to emerge that can
develop their own social media platforms
we are doing nothing we are mediocre we
have no ambition
and when i say me i'm not saying the
indian people it's the leadership
of india and that is and and we don't
have any
any investment in science where are the
particle accelerators where are the
scientific
experimental uh facilities do we have
any of those in india do we have any
any genuinely world-class astronomical
observatory do we have any institute
that's
only focused on research in physics and
chemistry and material science and
biology and biotechnology and all that
we have none of these things we don't
have even have an institute of institute
of genetics in india
when we find ancient artifacts and
ancient remains of human beings in india
we have to send the dna samples to korea
and the us to get them sequenced
we don't have a single lab in this
country which can do it it is the
government which
lacks ambition which lacks leadership
and
that's what's holding india back
so you are right it's the education
system which is a symptom of this lack
of ambition
and lacked lack of a vision for the
country
now think about people like einstein
boher planck
niels bohr was made a full professor a
head of department by the time he was 31
or
30 or 31 years old because he was the
best physicist in the country
right so he became the head of
department
of the of the best physics institute in
his country
at the age of 30 or 31 because he was
that good in
india if you are 30 or 31 you will not
rise
beyond the position of lecturer or
reader
you will not be made a full professor
unless you're until you're 40 or
something
your achievements accomplishments in
your quality
don't matter all that matters in india
is your seniority
and and how much how many connections
you have made
you know mathematicians have this belief
that a genuine world-class mathematician
will do his or her best work
before the age of 30. every
mathematician believes this and there's
a great deal of data that proves this
ramanujan is one example he did his
brilliant work before the age of 30.
if you take the best mathematicians of
any era
they have always done their best work
before the age of 30. and that's why
there is no mathematician in india of
any
of any note because if you want to go
into mathematical research in india
you have to go through the grind and you
will not reach a position where you can
do research
of your own volition without being told
what to do before the age of 40 or 45
and that's why india doesn't progress in
any of these fields
so yes you're right it is the system
which is holding this country back
akash asks does every field of education
have an equal contribution towards the
country's growth
or does science and technology play a
more crucial role
in deciding of a country's present
condition and prospects for
of a bright future
every field of education is not equal
it's the a country's progress always
depends only on one thing in science
it's scientific and technological
development look at the past 5000 years
of world history
the civilizations that have emerged
ahead of everyone else of every other
civilization
they have always been ahead of everyone
else in science and technology
especially applied science and
technology in military technology
and things like that so it's always
science and technology that
takes a nation forward yes we need arts
we need philosophy we need psychology
and various other allied fields etc but
they don't take the country forward it
is science and technology
and research and development that take
the country forward and positioning
and position the country among the top
two three or five nations in the world
and when it science and technology makes
the country prosperous it's
then that the other fields prosper it's
then that the arts prosper
and it's then that you have a
renaissance but you can't
aim for a renaissance before the country
is that prosperous because of science
and technology
so that's why if you want to bring
a genuine turn around in a country's
fortunes
you have to concentrate on science and
technology initially the first 20 30 40
years
then everything else can take over
but even then science and technology
have to be primary
junger singh johan asks after listening
to your videos when i listen to my
teacher teaching about the aryan
invasion the alleged iron invasion and
about the rigveda being written about
2500 bc
i find her knowledge very rudimentary
what should i do
should i argue with her which is
meaningless because at the end
that is what i'm supposed to have to
write in the exams so should i argue
with her or should i simply observe
you see in india's education system so
those students are not supposed to ask
questions they're not supposed to talk
back to teachers and they're
never supposed to argue if you argue
with your teacher she's going to make
your life miserable because she holds
all the power
and you will get less marks and there is
no point arguing with her because you're
not going to change her mind
she is a product of the same education
system that we are of
that we are all going through or have
gone through
and she believes what she believes that
i'm sure she's not a bad person but she
believes that whatever she learned was
right
and i don't know how old your teacher is
but after a certain age people
refuse to change they refuse to
entertain new ideas
and new possibilities so i would say my
friend
do not waste your time and energy
arguing with her or trying to convince
her
you know what is right you write your
exam
write whatever is required to get marks
and move on and do something good for
your country when you're in the in the
in a position to do so so don't waste
your time arguing
with your teacher it's entirely
pointless
vijaya vijay vijaya kumar asks what are
your views on japan's
career-based education system should
india adopt it
or is the gurukul system better i think
see the thing is this uh in the
late 19th century in the second half of
the 19th century
the japanese underwent what is called
the meiji reformation
so they tried to completely transform
the country they tried to copy the
western industrial system
and they reformed the education as well
in that they tried to stamp out buddhism
which failed etc
so the entire education system that you
have in japan this career-based
performance based education system is
a consequence of first of all the meiji
reformation
and then what happened after the second
world war in which japan focused
entirely on rebuilding the country
at a very rapid rate and they
were greatly influenced by the american
occupation of the country which still
continues by the way
japan is still under occupation by the
united united states
so all of these factors influence their
their education system their education
system is extremely stressful
okay but it does work it does produce
high performing people
who perform like robots in in the
various industries but it has
caused certain things which are not good
for japan the
uh total fertility rate in japan
the number of children a couple has has
fallen below the replacement rate
the um the average
age of the population of japan is
growing older and older
people are dying alone society is
breaking up i mean there are lots of
terrible things happening in japan the
suicide rates are high among students
etc
so japan is admirable in the sense that
it has embraced
modernity while holding on to its
ancient roots
it is a beautiful blend of ultra
modernity
with traditional values and traditional
culture and that culture is as i've
discussed before is
mainly dharmic culture infused and
syncretized with shinto so my point is
that
the they have done a great job of
modernizing the country it has worked
very well but it has caused
it has um imposed a very heavy toll on
the people psychologically mentally
and socially etc
so i think the japanese system is not
one that i would want to copy
india's ancient system was far better so
we need to try and find ways to
revive india's ancient system
but with 21st century characteristics
and with a very strong emphasis on
science and technology
and think about the future long term
om asks what is the future of
reservations and do you think
that in the future future we would be
able to remove reservations
and people would let that happen so i'll
tell you what
reservations are a political thing this
was imposed by politicians
in order to gain votes and today it's
it's gone like
it's it's it's uh it's run amok
it's it's going out of control
reservations are in the in the iit's
more than 60
of the seats are reserved now so i think
this is extremely detrimental for the
country reservations are
harming the country a country which is
not a meritocracy is a country which has
no future
it's destroying its own future right so
i think reservations need to be
abolished entirely and the best way to
abolish reservations
is to make the entire education system
entirely free
now i know it can't happen today or
tomorrow it will take a lead period
of reforms before we can achieve that so
i would say that we need to
have a target of the next 20 years the
20 years from today everything should be
free
and we need to start making a
step-by-step plan and implementing that
so that 20 years from today we can have
a fully fair and free
education system and when the education
system is entirely free there's no need
for reservations
especially when it is we have enough
educational institutions throughout the
country
to cater to every student because today
we have this artificial scarcity there
are very few
colleges and universities and there are
millions of students who need degrees
so the indian politicians have imposed
this culture of artificial scarcity
which
dates back to the 50s and 60s and 70s
the socialist days of the nerubian
regime
so we need to invest
in the future of the country by creating
this educational infrastructure
and doing these reforms and hopefully if
we start today
then 20 years from today or whenever we
start
someday then within 20 years we can have
a completely
free education system in which case we
will not need
reservations
and yeah yeah you all you also asked
whether people would let that happen
well people it is people who are
influenced by politics
who are in favor of reservations but
when you have sufficient number of
schools
colleges universities and when education
is free
then reservations will become pointless
and there will be no resistance
anymore so that it should be the
ultimate objective
okay indo asks there is a huge
discrepancy between the state board
standards at least in tamil nadu and
that of cbsc assuming it's better
do you think this could lead to poor
outcomes for the students
what do you suggest to be done should
there be a single standardized education
system that the entire
nation should be following i spoke about
this yesterday and you are right indo
there is this terrible discrepancy
throughout the country
every state has a state board then you
have the cbsc board and ntsc board and
god knows what other boards
so it's a complete hodgepodge it's like
we have a number of 15
20 30 50 different small sub nations
and some national identities within the
nation and there is no means of actually
rationally comparing the results of
these different boards so it is
extremely harmful and detrimental to the
long-term future of the country
what needs to happen is a single
standardized
system throughout the country every
state should have two languages
one is the civilizational language
sanskrit the second one is your
mother thing whatever it is in some
states you have two three different
local languages so let the student
choose whatever they want as the
other language and then you need to have
standardization
only one system the same curriculum the
same history
of course every state should also teach
their own local history which is very
important for the people to
have a sense of their roots so we need
to have a proper
rational system a standardized system
throughout the entire nation
that is what will cohesively integrate
the country
together and it will produce better
outcomes for every student
so we need to have this at the lower
education level up to the 10 standard
we need to have this at the higher
education level also today in higher
education you have the
bachelor's degree you have the master's
degree then you have the net exam the
set exam the sled exam then you have a
phd degree
in that you have entrance exams and pt
exams and even after you get a
phd you need to pass net or set or what
what not
to get a job it is a disastrously
ridiculous system
it needs to be rationalized it needs to
be revamped
it needs reforms we need standardization
we need standardized standardization in
the country so indu you are absolutely
right it is
it is very detrimental to the long-term
outcomes
for the individuals and for the country
it needs to be reformed we need
standardization
so that's what needs to happen
ishwar asks is the new education policy
2020 a good start for improving our
existing poor education system as you
have said the new policy is just like a
band-aid
on the shotgun wound so what are the
negatives of the new education policy
and what should the government do in
order to fix it so i
touched upon all the problems that we
have in the indian education system
yesterday in episode 30. does the
so-called
new education policy 2020 address
any of the problems does it address any
of the outcomes that we need
does it address the fact that the
education system does not treat the
student as the stakeholders
it it serves as an employment generation
scheme as a money making machine
it doesn't care about the future of the
students it doesn't care about the needs
of the students
it doesn't fulfill the needs of the
students it doesn't
put the students first it gives wrong
information wrong education
there is this emphasis on year once a
year exams
and there is this lack of
standardization there are so many
problems
i went into all the problems in detail
yesterday in episode 30
take a look at that episode so the new
education policy
does nothing nothing whatsoever
to address any of the real deep rooted
problems in india's education system and
that's why i
will say this again it is absolutely
useless
so what should the government do to fix
it well revamp the education system from
scratch from the very beginning
it there is no point taking an existing
system that is terrible
and try to change some small aspects of
it
the entire system has to go a new proper
system has to be brought in
you can't change the entire system in
one go so start from the very bottom
start from the lowest stage
or lowest grades of the education system
and start reforming
reforming from there and give yourself a
20-year period
a 20-year plan every year a new step is
taken
and that's how we reform the system
that's what needs to happen but we need
some
genuine leader who is who has the
gumption and the willingness and the
fortitude
to actually do something like this
all right will india become a superpower
one day a superpower that can defeat
china and europe and the usa if your
answer is yes then how much time do you
in how much time do you expect this to
happen
so like i showed yesterday becoming a
superpower
depends on the kind of education system
you have i showed the example of china
in great detail
how they have positioned themselves how
they have brought themselves in a
position
in which they can now think of genuinely
becoming a superpower
can india do this can india become a
superpower i would say that india will
either become a superpower in the next
20 years
or it will not be a superpower for the
next 100 years
the change needs to happen now genuine
change not this fake vote vote bank
changes
not the pandering to the vote banks and
all that we need a real change it has to
start with education
it has to start within with the war
against corruption it has to start with
opening up of the industries and
unleashing of the full economic
potential of india
and so many things need to happen
infrastructure building what not that
can
trigger the economy and trigger of a
great growth in the economy of the
country
so we have 20 years at most
it is definitely possible genuinely
possible for india to become a genuine
superpower
in one generation in the next 20 years
so my
prediction is that india will either
become
a superpower top three nation in the
next 20 years
or it will not be able to achieve that
in the next 100 years
that's my prediction and with that my
friends we come to the
close of these questions let me take a
look at what you are asking me in the
live chat i will take some live chat
questions now
okay bobby says if i travel to the
netherlands which i have
yeah sure even i have traveled there
they speak english as well as dutch if i
travel to the states they speak english
english needs to be incorporated as well
as sanskrit
have you traveled to china
have you traveled to china do they speak
chinese do they speak english there
99 of people will not speak english
there have you traveled to la france
have you gone to france
do people speak english there they will
refuse to speak english even if they
know english
they will speak to you in french unless
you have
big wards of greenbacks in that case
they'll speak to you in english
just to get your money there is a
certain amount of
cultural and civilizational pride in
certain nations
go to japan do people speak english
there no they speak
japanese go to korea how many
english-speaking people
do you find there let's not take the
example of europe and the united states
india is is not a colony of the of
european nations anymore
india is a civilization india is going
to rise as a civilization again
and the civilizational language of the
whole of asia
for thousands of years was sanskrit i do
not need
english english is an inferior language
it's a colonial language
it is holding india back we need to
reject
english we need to promote sanskrit
worldwide
if india becomes a superpower it needs
to spread sanskrit worldwide and make
sanskrit the universal
international lingua franca and the
language of science and education
that's what needs to happen reject
english
and it's it's i know it's it's ironical
that i am saying this in english
you see my generation and the present
generation we have been put through this
education system
in which english is the primary language
so it is
unfortunate that we employ
english and we are comfortable with
english to this extent
and that is something i understand i
recognize this fact
and i would like the future generations
to not be put through this trauma
so the future generations need to learn
sanskrit and their mother tongue
whatever the local languages
reject english
okay this has nothing to do with
education but let me answer it rishi
says
asks can india bangladesh and pakistan
united in the future
in the future i would like the whole of
india the whole of the indian
subcontinent to unite
as of today it's not possible there are
too many
cultural and religious differences it's
not going to be possible
in the next 20 30 50 years
but we can start putting the things in
place for this to happen
and future generations hopefully can see
our uni
reunified civilization in the future but
as of today it's not possible
in the future it is possible yes
when i went to japan the prayers in the
shrines were written in sanskrit like i
said sanskrit
is the original language
of high civilization and it and
sanskrit was never imposed upon the
japanese right it was not imposed
in a colonial way it was they absorbed
it
they accepted it they were happy to have
so that is the real status of sanskrit
and that's why i keep on
saying that we need to reinstate
sanskrit as our civilizational language
samia asks should army service be
compulsory well we have 1.3
billion people and we have an army which
has
a strength of about a million if
everybody were to let's say we are
trying to
put every child through one year of
compulsory army service
how will they be able to accommodate so
many people
right we have such an enormous
population so it is not
uh logistically uh
feasible right it's not practical for
everyone
to have compulsory army service and in
the case of israel
they have a very small population so
it's possible in the case of india it's
very difficult
if people are willing to do one year of
couples of army service
then maybe they can enter a lottery or
something and maybe we can take a
million per year or something
something like that if if we want to
consider it but
compulsory army army service is not
practical unfortunately
it is definitely desirable that
everybody should get an experience of
actual
uh military training and some kind of
at least mock combat experience that
would be good for sure
but it is not practical because of our
enormous population
hassan ishaan ishaan asks should indian
students go abroad to study
indian students should do whatever is
necessary for them to succeed in life
if you have to go abroad and to get a
better education
then go abroad and get a better
education if you have to settle abroad
go settle abroad and one day when india
is a far
better country then if you are in a good
position you can return
and offer your services and your
contribution to the country
but to do that to be valuable to your
civilization you have to first
acquire the tools to do so you have to
reach your full potential you have to
become the best version of yourself
so do whatever it takes right now when
you are 15 years old when you are 20
years old when you are a teenager when
you are in the early 20s
do whatever it takes to become the best
version of yourself go abroad settle
abroad doesn't matter
but remember where your true home is
and when the chance comes do come and
serve the country
asks do our leaders have the ambition to
change the education system well i am
not
one of your leaders so
i guess they don't as of today at least
we don't see that we have this i mean
this
new education policy or whatever it's
called nep
which is clearly written by bureaucrats
it does
nothing really so unfortunately as of
today as of 2021
july it doesn't look like we have a
leader who has the ambition or the or
the vision to change the education
system
maybe in august or september maybe we
may have somebody i don't know
as of today we don't have somebody who
does this
okay ratio says uh he's talking to
somebody we can start a startup which
provides old indigenous education
system well you know the thing about
startups is that they have to be
financially successful they have to be
economically successful they have to
uh they are sustainable only if they
bring in profits
quarter upon quarter profits and the old
indian education system
was based upon no profits it was
subsidized by the state
it was subsidized by the community it
was a king
or the queen who contributed sufficient
funds to keep it running
so there was no profit in it there was
they did not ever
ask students for fees the education was
completely free
and that is the entire complete
anti-thesis of a startup
a startup is all about profits so that
is not the way to go about it
unfortunately i'm not trying to
discourage you
i'm glad you're thinking differently but
a proper education system especially the
ancient indian education system was
always subsidized and supported by the
state by the
king by the civilization by the
community everybody pitched in
that is the reason why whenever we go to
temples we give some kind of donation
there
the majority of that money was used for
the upkeep of the education
of the education system because temples
were the center of education
this system was destroyed by the british
about 150 200 years ago
but we still haven't forgotten the act
of
donating contributing money to temples
and now that money is being stolen
by the by the government and being used
for
secular purposes which is such a
shame
am i randomly picking comments from live
chat yes now i am
yes you have a question ask me i'll try
and pick it up
dhruv asks why do uneducated people hold
ministries in india
it's because politics runs on the
principle of
power you may be uneducated but you have
power political power you know how to
get votes
you know how to get people on the
streets you know how to get things done
you know how to
effect change politically that gives you
power if you have power
you have political currency power is the
currency of politics
education doesn't matter unfortunately
that's the system we have and it's very
funny to see that
image you have there so that's that's
the problem you see
okay let me take a couple more questions
about education
how okay prithvi asks how can we educate
ourselves if we don't have enough money
to study abroad
that is unfortunate most of us don't
have money i mean
the per capita income in india is is
quite less it's very hard
for parents in india to send the
children abroad unless they are able to
gain a scholarship or something which is
like
which is which doesn't happen all the
time so if you
don't have enough money to study abroad
get an education in india
do the best you can the best school
university college whatever you can
get into get your education get your
degree and then see how it goes and
keep on educating yourself outside
of the education system gain some actual
skills
i would always say that gain some
technical skills some computational
skills some high-tech skills you know
because technology is the future so try
and get some skills gain some skills
online
which are not part of the education
system which are beyond your degree
but those skills can always come in
handy when you are young you should
acquire as many skills and as many
experiences as possible
so it doesn't matter if you don't have
enough money to go abroad
don't be discouraged the world is
changing
in the future in the very very
short-term future we're gonna see that
uh employment and jobs will depend
more and more on skills they're going to
place more and more
priority on skills many big companies in
the u.s are now
no longer requiring that people have
degrees all they see is what skills you
have what's the kind of portfolio you
build up
so things are going to change very soon
so don't be discouraged
keep stay positive and acquire and do
the best you can
with whatever resources you have and the
world is your oyster in the future
okay i'll take one more question
praveen asks do we need entrance exams
like jee math
um for prime colleges or should there be
any other means for
admission i think we need to have just
one standard exam
one standard exam for the depending on
whatever stream you've chosen whether
you've chosen
a scientific stream an engineering
stream or whatever
there needs to be just one common
entrance exam and depending on the
percentile or whatever you got you
should be able to get admission in
various schools
various colleges universities etc we
have so many
entrance exams it becomes an impossible
burden for children for for students
so we need rationalization of the
education system
as of today this is what we have so if
you want to succeed you have to go
through it i would not
i am not by any means trying to tell you
that you should not go study for the ge
or whatever
as of today you have to so do it what
i'm talking about is
what we should do in the future long
term in the next five 10 20 years
as of today you have to go through this
unfortunately so do it do the best you
can
okay one last question what do we have
niraj kumar singh asks do you think that
in the in order to improve the education
system
one party nation is better than
multi-party nation as one party nation
can enforce the long-term vision
well what you are saying well you you
you're right in a sense because the
chinese are a one-party nation they're a
dictatorship
they are a totalitarian pseudo-marxist
pseudo-imperialistic nation
and they have one party which is why
they're able to enforce a long-term
vision
in india every five years or whatever
period of time it takes for a new
political dispensation to come to power
things keep changing things keep
changing there is no continuity there is
no long-term vision
so yes when a country is in a state like
the
like india is in it's a it's a
underdeveloped country
country with a great deal of poverty
great deal of problems
it does help if you have political
stability for about a period of about 20
years
now i am not advocating any form of
dictatorship i abhor dictatorship
but we need to find some solution to it
to to ensure there is
political continuity and there is an
there is a
push in the direction of the long-term
national interest
in the long in the long term in the end
it doesn't matter whether you have a
one-party nation multi-party nation
all that matters is whether the national
interest is being served
and if the if the national interest is
being served by a one-party nation
i am happy with it if it is being served
by a multi-party system
i'm happy with that as well there are
many ways like they say to skin a cat
right it doesn't matter whether the cat
is black or white as long as it catches
mice
that's what the chinese say so we need
to find a solution
to what we have right of right now the
political system is
unstable and it it basically
does not prioritize the long-term
interests of the nation so that needs to
change
okay my friends thank you so much for
watching thank you so much for
participating
this was great talking about education
thank you so much and i will see you
very soon in the next episode
have a good night have a good day take
care bye